Inventory of the J.E. Morpurgo Papers 1937-2000
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
J.E. Morpurgo Papers, 1742, 1937-2000, 1950-1970
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 2001 M67
ca. 3,700 items.
Papers, 1937-2000, bulk 1950-1970, of Jack Morpurgo, writer, educator, and editor. Includes correspondence; speeches; lectures; radio scripts; published and unpublished essays, articles, and novels; certificates and awards; photographs; and framed prints.
Morpurgo, J. E.;; Blunden, Edmund, 1896-1974;; Adair, Virginia, 1913-;; Forte, Charles, 1908-;; Nye, Russel Blaine, 1913-.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Acc. No. 2001-4; Gift: ca. 3,700 items, 01/2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
Jack Morpurgo (1918-2000) graduated from Christ's Hospital School in England. He was the first British graduate of the College of William and Mary in Virginia after the American Revolution. He served in the British military during World War II. In his professional life, he was an editor and author of fiction and non-fiction. He was a frequent contributor of articles and book reviews to magazines, scholarly journals, and newspapers. He wrote and participated in numerous radio and television broadcasts in Britain, the United States, Canada, and Australia. A significant portion of his career was spent under the tutelage of Alan Lane, founder of Penguin Books.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1937-2000, bulk 1950-1970, of Jack Morpurgo, writer, educator, and editor. Includes correspondence, speeches, lectures, radio scripts, published and unpublished essays, articles, and novels, books from his personal library, certificates and awards, photographs, and framed prints. Most of the collection consists of Morpurgo's personal writings and business correspondence related to his work as a professor, editor, and director of the National Book League. Morpurgo was a British citizen and graduate of Christ's Hospital school. During his career, he wrote extensively on the subject of Christ's Hospital school. The school was founded in 1552 as a charity to benefit needy children with shelter, food, clothing, and an education. By the eighteenth century, Christ's Hospital was known as one of England's great public schools. It continues to educate British children in the twenty-first century. The papers include correspondence with Edmund Blunden, Virginia Hamilton Adair, Charles Forte, and Russel B. Nye.
Organization
This Collection has been organized into 20 series: Series 1. Correspondence and biographical material; Series 2. Correspondence relating to writing projets; Series 3. Records relating to Christ's Hospital; Series 4. Papers relating to the College of William & Mary Series; 5. Papers relating to the University of Leeds Series; 6. Teaching materials Series; 7. Speeches; Series 8. Papers relating to WW II and the military; Series 9. Articles; Series 10. Papers related to the History of the Book-Readers, Writers, Publishers; Series 11. Papers related to Penguin Publishing; Series 12. Essays on Literature; Series 13. Book reviews; Series 14. Papers relating to books by J.E.M.; Series 15. Writings; Series 16. Genealogical information; Series 17. Miscellaneous Non-J.E.M.; Series 18. Photographs; Series 19. Artifacts, prints, awards; Series 20: Audio materials; Series 21. Library.
Index Terms
Persons:
Blunden, Edmund, 1896-1974.; Adair, Virginia, 1913-.; Forte, Charles, 1908-.; .; Nye, Russel Blaine, 1913-.
Corporate name:
College of William and Mary--History--20th century.; Penguin (Firm)--History.; Christ's Hospital (Horsham, England)--History.
Subjects:
Publishers and publishing--Great Britain-- Biography.; English teachers--Great Britain--Biography.; Historians--Great Britain--Biography.
Geographical name:
United States--Description and travel.; United States--Civilization.; Europe--Civilization--American influences.
Contents List
  Series 1: Correspondence and biographical material
- Correspondence and biographical material, n.d., 1927-2000. (Box-folder 1:1-30b)
  - Biographical information, n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Resume, curriculum vitae, lists of publications, talks, and speeches.
  - Autobiographical essays on life and career, n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Published information on J.E.M., n.d., 1939-1953., 15 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Sources include The New Yorker, The Observer, The William and Mary Alumni Gazette, and others. Also includes a complete December 1952 issue of Thirty-One Four, the staff publication of the Continental Bank and Trust Company of Salt Lake City, Utah. J.E.M. had visited their offices in November 1952. N.B. article on page 5.
  - Christmas greetings, 1927-1933., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Greetings from Frances and Gilbert Chesterton. Each card contains a poem by Frances Chesterton.
  - Documents relating to expense accounts and retainers, 1951-1954., 27 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Principia Alumni Purpose, Summer 1966, 1966., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Journal of Principia College, St. Louis, Missouri. Contains an interview with J.E.M. conducted by Principia student, Neil Soderstrom (pp. 4-7).
  - Elmira College Collection, June 1966., 19 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Album presented to J.E.M. who was commencement speaker. Includes honorary doctorate, programs, press clippings, and photographs.
  - John Richmond, Writing in Three Dimensions, 10 October 1970., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:8)
    Canadian newspaper. Includes interview with J.E.M.
  - Correspondence between J.E.M. and Rosalind Young, September-October 1972., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
    Correspondence between J.E.M. and Rosalind Young of the British Council Specialist Tours Department, regarding J.E.M.'s trip to Mexico, Venezuela, and Chile.
  - Correspondence between General S. Shahid Hamid, Minister for Information and Broadcasting, Pakistan, n.d., 7 June 1979., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Church service program, 27 February 1980., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:11)
    Program from A Service of Thanksgiving for the Life and Work of Sir Barnes Wallis. Held at St. Paul's Cathedral. The Address was delivered by J.E.M.
  - Correspondence with Dawn Muirhead, 1983., 10 items. (Box-folder 1:12)
    Correspondence with Dawn Muirhead and information concerning the Washington Project, a memorialization of George Washington.
  - College of Idaho, Caldwell, Idaho, 1979-1986., 8 items. (Box-folder 1:13)
    Items related to J.E.M.'s time as scholar in residence at the College of Idaho, Caldwell, Idaho. Includes honorary doctorate.
  - Honorary Doctorate from Rocky Mountain College, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:13a (moved to medium oversize))
  - Correspondence re memorial volume for Arthur B. (Tim) Hanson, ca. 1989., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:14)
    Correspondence regarding republication of part of J.E.M.'s autobiography in a memorial volume about Arthur B. (Tim) Hanson, a friend and fellow alumnus of William and Mary. Includes the extract to be used and a biographical sketch of Hanson.
  - Christmas letters, 1995., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:15)
    Christmas letters to J.E.M. One signed "Kay" of East Lansing; the other in German.
  - Virginia Hamilton Adair, 1995-1998., 18 items. (Box-folder 1:16)
    Correspondence by and about Virginia Hamilton Adair. Includes copies of some of her poems.
  - Church service bulletin, 20 March 1993., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:17)
    Bulletin from "Service of Thanksgiving for the life and love of Catherine Noel Kippe Morpurgo, 1918-1993." The Church of the Holy Innocents, London.
  - Obituary for J.E.M. from Colonial Williamsburg Magazine, Winter 200-2001, 2001., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Correspondence concerning Edmund Blunden, 1945-1983., 47 items. (Box-folder 1:19)
    Includes one photocopied letter from Blunden to J.E.M. dated 19 April 1945. Also includes correspondence from 23 January 1974 to 25 July 1983 concerning the death of Edmund Blunden and the publishing of his poetry, his memorial, and correspondence with his widow, Claire.
  - Personal correspondence, 1940s., 152 items. (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Personal correspondence, 1960s., 14 items. (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Personal correspondence, 1970s., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Personal correspondence, 1980s., 20 items. (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Personal correspondence, 1990s, 144 items. (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Correspondence with Nan Hodges, 1961-2000., 90 items. (Box-folder 1:25)
    J.E.M.'s correspondence with William and Mary alumna, Nan Hodges.
  - J.E.M.: "Warm Welcome at Tel Afar: A Fragment of Autobiography", n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:26)
    Short story by J.E.M., later published in his autobiography, "Master of None". Includes both versions.
  - Carman Barnes: "The Englishman is Rather Sad", n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:27)
    Essay by Carman Barnes, in which the author writes of J.E.M.'s views on the English and Americans. Contains direct quotes from a conversation between the author and J.E.M.
  - Miscellaneous handwritten notes and drafts, n.d., 10 items. (Box-folder 1:28)
  - J.E.M, Entrance to the Aviary, September 1979., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:29)
    Published in Quadrant, pages 43-49. Adapted from his autobiography, Master of None.
  - Correspondence regarding Anglo-American relations, September 1979., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:30)
    Correspondence from Lorin or Louis[?] of Antioch College, Yellow Springs, Ohio, dealing with Anglo-American relations. Signed only with first name. The writer was probably a Professor at the College.
  - J.E.M. Honorary Doctor of Letters and college shield from Ricker College, Houlton, Maine, 12 June 1961., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:30a)
  - Toronto Public Library, Boys and Girls House, 7 May 1964., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:30b)
    Opening of Boys and Girls House of the Toronto Public Library; memorabilia. Includes drawing of the building, order of proceedings, and J.E.M. commemorative card.
  Series 2: Correspondence relating to writing projects
- Correspondence relating to writing projects, 1955-1993. (Box-folder 1:31-41b)
  - Letter to J.E.M. from Elizabeth E. Hamer, Assistant Librarian of Congress, 27 May 1970., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:31)
    Letter concerning the Bicentennial program.
  - Correspondence regarding an exhibition on books for school libraries organized by the National Book League, 1955-1956., 7 items. (Box-folder 1:32)
    Includes criticism of the exhibit from The Journal of Education.
  - Correspondence related to J.E.M.'s article "Albany" in The Book of Westminster, 1962-1964., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:33)
  - Letter to J.E.M. from Patricia Edwards, Secretary to Mr. Robin Winks of the United States Information Service in the American Embassy, London, 30 January 1970., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:34)
    Includes a review of Hortense Calisher's The New Yorkers from the Times Literary Supplement.
  - Correspondence between J.E.M. and Bruce King, Department of English, University of Windsor, Ontario, Canada, 1971-1972., 15 items. (Box-folder 1:35)
    Deals with J.E.M.'s contribution to an anthology edited by King. Includes unsigned copy of agreement with publisher, Routledge and Kegan Paul and a letter from J.E.M to Sally Spiller, of Routledge, disputing contract terms. Eventually King found someone else to write J.E.M.'s section, as he was too busy.
  - Correspondence with Blackwood's Magazine concerning stories submitted to and published by the magazine, 1977-1980., 25 items. (Box-folder 1:36)
    Includes copies of the stories.
  - Correspondence with Quadrant Magazine concerning stories submitted to and published by the magazine, 1979-1982., 38 items. (Box-folder 1:37)
  - Note from Dr. A. Massa to J.E.M. regarding lecture topics in American literature, 11 December 1980., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:38)
    Includes suggestion list.
  - Correspondence between J.E.M. and Michael Parnell, a lecturer in English at the Polytechnic Institute of Wales, 1982., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:39)
    Letters deal with writer Eric Linklater, an acquaintance of J.E.M.
  - Correspondence to J.E.M. from Steven Tuohy of the Printing Historical Society regarding J.E.M.'s tribute to Hugh Williamson to be published in the March 1993 Bulletin, 1993., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:40)
    Includes a draft of J.E.M. contribution.
  - Correspondence between J.E.M. and Ms. V.G.I. Smith, January-February 1992., 4 items. (Box-folder 1:41)
    Correspondence regards questions after reading Barnes Wallis: A Biography. She hoped J.E.M. could give her information about her father.
  - Yorkshire Post Award, 27 March 1980., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:41a (moved to medium oversize box).)
  Series 3: Papers relating to Christ's Hospital
- Papers relating to Christ's Hospital (Box-folder 2:1-28)
  Christ's Hospital School was founded in the City of London by King Edward VI in 1552, with the purpose to provide needy children with shelter and education that would enable them to be selfsufficient after their release. From the 17th to the mid-18th century, pupils educated in penmanship, bookkeeping and accounting were apprentised to merchants, lawyers, and other professionals in overseas colonies.
    Subseries 3.1: Speeches, essays and records relating to the History of Christ's Hospital
  - Speeches, essays and records relating to the History of Christ's Hospital (Box-folder 2:1-18)
    - List of students of the Royal Mathematical School, Christ's Hospital, for the years 1675-1742, n.d., 1 item, transcription. (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Detailed records of children released from Christ's Hospital to indentured apprentice positions on ships bound for the colonies, 1675-1821, n.d., 1694, 1697, 1997. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Included are photocopies of a 1694 and a 1697 list of children released from Christ's Hospital between 1675-1697, and "put forth to the Practice of Navigation". The records list the dates of indenture and the names of the masters. Also included are typed and ms. transcriptions of various detail of Christ's Hospital records, listing information on children discharged between 1784-1821: the name of the colony they were bound to serve in, length of indenture, date of birth and admission, name of parents, and name of the masters.
    - Lists of children from Christ's Hospital, London, who were apprenticed between 1675-1887 on ships headed for the Americas and other British colonies, 1767-1887, 1988, 1998., 4 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
      Includes photocopies of a printed list, 1769, of apprentices, released between 1675-1767, photocopies of a ms. list of apprentices released 1767-1887, a letter dated 3 March 1998 written to J.E.M. from Christ's Hospital regarding the microfilming and copying of the above records, and an article on Christ's Hospital apprentices from Colonial Williamsburg Magazine, 1988.
    - Outlook - The literary magazine published at Christ's Hospital, April 1936., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Includes "An Essay on Drink, Drinking and Drinkers, Borrowed from most Authors, Ancient and Modern, Sacred and Profane," credited to J.E.M.
    - J.E.M.: A Somerset Athlete, Winter 1948-1949., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:5)
      In: The West Country Magazine, pp. 280-283.
    - Letter from Christ's Hospital to J.E.M. regarding the Master Mariner's Prize, 11 November 1980., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:6)
    - J.E.M. Founder's Day Speech, Christ's Hospital, 1979., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:7)
    - J.E.M. speech delivered to President and Gentlemen at Christ's Hospital, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Extracts from Professor [J.E.] Morpurgo's Speech Proposing the Health of the Chairman, Roy Salisbury, Clerk of Christ's Hospital, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:9)
    - After-dinner oration delivered to alumni at Christ's Hospital, 25 October 1968., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Christ's Hospital - An Introductory History by J. E. Morpurgo, with a bibliography, n.d., 1 item (62 pp.). (Box-folder 2:11)
      .
    - J.E.M.: Four Hundred Years of Blue-Coat Boys, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:12)
      Published essay.
    - J.E.M.: A Famous English School, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:13)
    - J.E.M.: Essay on Christ's Hospital, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:14)
    - J.E.M.: Speeches and articles on old blues and Christ's Hospital, 1960-1970., 8 items. (Box-folder 2:15)
    - J.E.M.: Articles in Colonial Williamsburg Magazine, 1988, 1999/2000, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:16)
      Articles: Autumn 1988: A Thing Without Parallel - Christ's Hospital and America, (pp. 7-14); December 1999/January 2000: untitled essay related to Summer 1995 article, Journey With Ghosts, (pp. 6-7). Includes note from Dennis Montgomery, Colonial Williamsburg Journal Office, about J.E.M. contribution, dated 15 June 2000.
    - Obituary for Hon. David Roberts, a Senior History Master at Christ's Hospital, by J.E.M., n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:17)
    - Correspondence between J.E.M. and Paul Wade, 25 and 28 January 1972., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:18)
      Correspondence re contribution to British-American alumni magazine, Griffin. Wade was chairman of British-American alumni and Christ's Hospital. Mentioning of Christ's Hospital.
    Subseries 3.2: J.E.M. writings relating to Christ's Hospital alumni
  - J.E.M. writings relating to Christ's Hospital alumni, n.d., 1974, 1982. (Box-folder 2:19-25)
    - J.E.M.: Edmund Blunden: Poet of Community, 1974., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:19)
      In: Contemporary Review, pp. 192-198.
    - J.E.M.: The Education of Genius, n.d., 2 items (drafts, 34 and 15 pp.) (Box-folder 2:20)
    - J.E.M.: Untitled essay on Edmund Blunden, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:21)
    - J.E.M.: Pip - A Postscript, 1982., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:22)
      From: All I Did Was This - Chapters of an Autobiography by Youngman Carter. Nashville: Sexton Press. (pp. 88-90).
    - J.E.M.: Two essays on James Henry Leigh Hunt, n.d., 2 items (14 and 16 pp.). (Box-folder 2:23)
    - J.E.M.: Harold Skimpole's Better Half, 1948., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:24)
      Introduction to the Autobiography of Leigh Hunt. London: Cresset. (pp. vii-xxiv).
    - J.E.M.: Essay on Charles Lamb, n.d., 1 item (20 pp.). (Box-folder 2:25)
    Subseries 3.3: Additional records relating to Christ's Hospital
  - Additional records relating to Christ's Hospital (Box-folder 2:26-28)
    - Sir John Squire: A Credential and a Testament, 13 June 1953., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:26)
      In: The Illustrated London News (p. 980). Review of The Christ's Hospital Book, published to celebrate the 400th anniversary of the school.
    - J.E.M.: Notes for an article on Christ's Hospital and early residents of Williamsburg for Colonial Williamsburg Magazine, 2000., 17 items. (Box-folder 2:27)
    - The Blue, 1996-1998., 4 items. (Box-folder 2:28)
      Issues of The Blue mentioning J.E.M. Also programs from Old Blues' and Parent's Day from 21 June 1998 and 22 June 1997.
  Series 4: Papers relating to the College of William & Mary
- Papers relating to the College of William & Mary, 1936-1986. (Box-folder 2:29-45a)
  - J.E.M. classnotes, ca.1936., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:29)
    Notebook from class in American Social History at William and Mary.
  - J.E.M. classnotes from History and Literature classes, n.d., 13 items. (Box-folder 2:30)
  - J.E.M.: "Critique of Reconstruction in Philosophy by John Dewey," December 1937., items. (Box-folder 2:31)
    Essay, read in Contemporary Philosophy Seminar at William and Mary.
  - Bill McCann: Seeing America First, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:32)
    The Middleville Sun and Caledonia News. Written by a friend of J.E.M. after reading American Excursion (1949). Includes observations on William and Mary.
  - Letter from J.E.M. to Dr. Douglass Adair, Institute of Early American Studies, Williamsburg, Virginia, 12 January 1951., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:33)
  - Article on J.E.M, May 1963., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:34)
    In: Alumni Gazette of the College of William and Mary in Virginia.
  - Letter from Office of the Dean, the College of William and Mary, to J.E.M, 9 March 1967., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:35)
    Deals with J.E.M. as author of a college history.
  - Jamestown Day Address, by Dr. Davis Y. Paschall, President of the College of William and Mary, 12 May 1968., Autographed, 1 item. (Box-folder 2:36)
    Published by the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities.
  - United Kingdom Chapter of William and Mary Alumni Society, 1969-1973., 8 items. (Box-folder 2:37)
    Certificate and various letters and documents relating to founding of United Kingdom Chapter of William and Mary Alumni Society.
  - Citation to J.E.M. from William and Mary, 1970., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:38)
    Re: conferral of Degree of Doctor of Human Letters, Honoris Causa. Charter Day Program, 7 February 1970.
  - J.E.M.: Cherry Trees and Lions' Tails, 1972., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:39)
    Griffin: The Journal of the British American Alumni and the British American Educational Foundation, Inc. Article on page 11. TMS of article. Letter from J.E.M. to Griffin Editor regarding a printer's mistake in his essay.
  - Citation from Colin R. Davis to J.E.M. from for the William and Mary Alumni Society Medallion for service and loyalty, 1972., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:40)
  - Publication of Their Majesties' Royall Colledge, 1972-1982., 145 items. (Box-folder 2:41)
    Notes and correspondence concerning publication of Their Majesties' Royall Colledge, a history of the College of William and Mary. Includes correspondence with the President of the College, Thomas R. Graves, Jr. Includes a copy of Graves's Inaugural Address, 5 February 1972.
  - Press releases, 1973., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:42)
    Press release about the U.K. Alumni of William and Mary dinner, 17 May 1973. TMS. Press release about a dinner at the House of Commons to honor William and Mary President, Dr. Thomas A. Graves. 15 March 1973. TMS.
  - Charter Day commemorative booklet, 1976., 7 items. (Box-folder 2:43)
    Also included are newspaper clippings, a promotional leaflet for J.E.M., Their Majesties' Royall Colledge-William and Mary in the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries.
  - Constance Stapleton: A House Fit for a President, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:44)
    Article on the President's House at William and Mary, in: Americana (pp. 50-57).
  - Information on Phi Beta Kappa, the Flat Hat Club, and Williamsburg, 1916-1986., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:45)
  - J.E.M.'s Phi Beta Kappa Certificate, 6 December 1948., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:45a)
  - J.E.M.: B.A. and Honorary Doctorate from William and Mary, 1938, 1970., 2 items (moved to medium oversize box). (Box-folder 2:45b)
  Series 5: Papers relating to the University of Leeds
- Papers relating to the University of Leeds, 1968-1981. (Box-folder 2:45b-47)
  - Robert Lowell to J.E.M, 24 January 1970., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:46)
    Note from Robert Lowell to J.E.M. regarding J.E.M. as Lowell's presenter for degree at Leeds.
  - Programs for the Conferment of Honorary Degrees, The University of Leeds, 23 May 1968, 18 October 1976, 11 May 1977., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:47)
  - J.E.M.: Essay on William Walsh for the University of Leeds Review, 1981., 4 items. (Box-folder 2:48)
    Includes correspondence with the Editor.
  Series 6: Teaching materials
- Teaching materials, n.d., 1945-1970. (Box-folder 3:1-29)
  - J.E.M. lecture: The American Constitution, Summer 1945., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Lecture delivered to a Tutor's course at Oxford University.
  - Student's essays from seminar in Romantic Literature taught by J.E.M., 1948., 3 items. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Bibliographies of works by e.e. cummings and William Faulkner, 1969., 6 items. (Box-folder 3:3)